Guide to the Mardette Perkins Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Mardette Perkins papers
1942-1996
YCAL MSS 782
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
6.22
(20 boxes)
The papers provide insight into the personal and professional life of Mardette Perkins, American actress and poet, and consist of correspondence, drafts of writings, clippings, ephemera, computer media, and audiovisual material dating from 1942 to 1996. Perkins' acting career is represented in photographs, clippings, ephemera, and a film of her work for television commercials. The papers contain drafts of Perkins' poetry, including an unpublished manuscript for her "Collected Poems, I," and recordings of her reading poetry. The papers also shed light on Perkins' experience of psychoanalysis, detailed in her journals from 1961 to 1976.
Perkins, Mardette
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mardette Perkins, 1997-1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 11 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 19 (audiocassettes): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 20 (film): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Mardette Perkins (1924-2002)
Mardette Perkins, American actress, was born Margaret Hariot Edwards to Rev. H. Boyd Edwards, Sr. and Margaret Edwards on November 24, 1924 in Little Rock, Arkansas. She attended St. Margaret's School in Waterbury, CT., Wellesley College (1942-1946), and the Yale School of Drama (1946-1948). She married Robert Wilder Perkins on January 31, 1959 with whom she had sons Charles and Morgan. She died on May 23, 2002.
Perkins appeared in stage productions of "The Man Who Came for Dinner" (Plymouth Theater, 1949) and "Heartbreak House" (Bleeker Street Theatre, 1950). Her work for television includes "The Chair" (Armstrong Circle Theatre, 1950), "The Seventh Veil" (Lucky Strike Theatre, 1950), "The Symbol" (Philco-Goodyear Television Playhouse, 1951), "Murder for Laura" (The Web), "In Small Packages (Trapped), and "Jane Eyre" (Kraft Theatre, 1951), among others. Perkins also appeared on television in commercials for Borden's Coffee and General Electric.
Scope and Contents
The papers provide insight into the personal and professional life of Mardette Perkins, American actress and poet, and consist of correspondence, drafts of writings, clippings, ephemera, computer media, and audiovisual material dating from 1942 to 1996. Perkins' acting career is represented in photographs, clippings, ephemera, and a film of her work for television commercials. The papers contain drafts of Perkins' poetry, including an unpublished manuscript for her "Collected Poems, I," and recordings of her reciting poetry. The papers also shed light on Perkins' experience of psychoanalysis, detailed in her journals from 1961 to 1976.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence, 1948-1996. II. Writings, 1942-1996. III. Professional Papers, 1945-1966. IV. Personal Papers, 1948-1991. V. Audiovisual Material, 1961-1993.
Actors -- United States; American literature -- 20th Century; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Women and psychoanalysis; Women authors; Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Photographic prints; Sound recordings; Actors -- United States; Poets -- United States; Perkins, Mardette
- Series I. Correspondence, 1948-1996; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains personal and professional correspondence, dating from 1948 to 1981. Correspondents include Perkins' family members as well as Craig Biddle, a reverend at Perkins' church, with whom she fell in love. In her correspondence with curator Pat Willis at the Beinecke Library Perkins provides information about her life and family history.
  - Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, 1973-1996 (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence with curator Pat Willis and autobiographical notes describing Mardette Perkins' genealogy, professional career, writing, and personal life.
  - Biddle, Craig, 1973-1979; 2 (Box 1)
  - Boyd, Jeffrey H., 1988, undated (Box 1)
    Includes notes and other material relating to Jeffrey H. Boyd's book, which Perkins provided feedback on.
  - Fiddler, Andrew, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
    Includes notes and clippings.
  - Straight, Ms., circa 1950 (Box 1)
    Outgoing letter in which Perkins requests a meeting with Straight regarding a part in production of "The Innocence."
  - Family correspondence, 1976-1981; 2 (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence with husband Robert W. Perkins, brother H. Boyd Edwards and family, Perkins' sons Charlie and Morgan Perkins, their school teachers, and various friends.
  - Various correspondence, 1948-1979; 7 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence with friends, family and others, a project proposal for a playwrights' workshop, and letters to the Connecticut State Legislature regarding long term care insurance. Correspondents include: Gabriel J. Biafore, Mary Teresa Boyd, Robert Giaimo, Senator Mark H. Powers, Senator Philip S. Robertson, Ron Smoko, Ricky Weiser, and Frank Yulo.
- Series II. Writings, 1942-1996; 3.34; (9 boxes)
  The series contains drafts, a computer disk, and other material pertaining to Perkins' poetry dating from 1942 to 1996.
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  - Early Poems, autograph manuscripts, 1942-1943; 3 (Box 3)
  - Volume 1, autograph manuscripts, first drafts, 1967 July 10 - 1970 April 1; 2 (Box 3)
  - Volume 2, autograph manuscripts, revisions, 1967 July 10 - 1970 April 1; 2 (Box 4)
  - Volume 3a, autograph manuscripts, revisions, 1971; 2 (Box 4)
  - Autograph manuscripts and typescripts, corrected, 1967-1974 (Box 4)
    Includes title page with working title "In Between (The End and the Beginning)."
  - Typescripts, corrected, #1 - #3, 1973-1989; 3 (Box 5)
    Includes audience reactions from poetry reading at Colby College (1971).
  - Typescripts, corrected, includes some autograph manuscripts, 1968-1972 (Box 5)
  - Typescripts, corrected, includes autograph manuscript, 1974-1984 (Box 5)
  - "Collected Poems, I", 1942-1974
    - Typescripts, corrected, "revisions to back up 'M.S. Collected Poems' in Beinecke", 1970-1994; 2 (Box 6)
    - Typescripts, corrected, "originals and revisions to poems in M.S. at Beinecke", 1969-1994 (Box 6)
    - Typescripts, corrected, "early version, revision, for Beinecke", 1993-1994 (Box 6)
    - Autograph manuscripts and typescripts, corrected, "revision duplicates to back-up M.S. in Beinecke", 1971-1996 (Box 7)
    - Typescripts, corrected, "revisions to poems in m.s. at Beinecke", 1970-1993 (Box 7)
    - Autograph manuscripts and typescripts, corrected, "originals, revisions for M.S. Beinecke", 1980-1993 (Box 7)
    - Autograph manuscripts and typescripts, corrected, "back-up to m.s. in Beinecke", 1971-1982 (Box 7)
    - Autograph manuscript and typescripts, corrected, "revisions to back-up M.S. collected Poems in Beinecke", 1985-1993 (Box 7)
    - Typescripts, corrected, "revision and proofing to back-up m.s. collected Poems in Beinecke", 1990-1994 (Box 7)
    - Autograph manuscripts and typescripts, corrected, "first versions and early versions of poems, Phyllis Gibson typed for final M.S.", 1993-1994 (Box 7)
    - Typescripts, corrected, 1993-1994; 3 (Box 7)
    - Empty binders, "Collected Poems, I," 2nd set, 3 (Box 8)
    - Typescript, corrected, with table of contents and alphabetical listing of poems, undated (Box 9)
    - Typescript, 1-2 of 4 folders, circa 1994; 2 (Box 9)
    - Typescript, 3-4 of 4 folders, circa 1994; 2 (Box 10)
    - "Alphabetical List for Perkins' manuscript", [1999?]; (2 computer disks)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Box 11 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      Copies of electronic files are available through Access Services.
      1997-ycal-0220-ae-0001-0002
      - Alpha list Alphabetical order Mardette Perkins Poems, 1997-ycal-0220-ae-0001; 1 (Box 11)
        Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - Cormier policy/procedures Perkins Manuscript order, 1997-ycal-0220-ae-0002; 1 (Box 11)
  - Unidentified, outline and notes, undated (Box 10)
- Series III. Professional Papers, 1945-1966; 0.21; (1 box)
  The series contains resumes, contacts, headshots and other photographs, clippings, and ephemera relating to Perkins' acting career, dating from 1945 to 1966.
  - CV, undated (Box 12)
  - Contracts, 1948-1949 (Box 12)
  - Actor's Equity correspondence, membership cards, and other ephemera, 1947-1964 (Box 12)
  - American Federation of Television and Radio Artists, correspondence, membership cards, and other ephemera, 1952-1964 (Box 12)
  - Screen Actor's Guild, membership cards and receipts, 1954-1966; 2 (Box 12)
  - Publicity photographs with CV on reverse side, undated (Box 12)
  - Dangerous Corner, stage production program, 1949 (Box 12)
  - The Man who Came to Dinner, photograph, 1949 (Box 12)
    "Mardette Edwards, Don Peters, and Monty Woolley in a stage comedy scene from The Man Who Came to Dinner, starring Mr. Woolley in person."--note on reverse side.
  - The Man Who Came to Dinner, 3 stage production programs, 1949 (Box 12)
  - Plymouth Drama Festival Alumni Association card, 1945 (Box 12)
  - Clippings of stage productions in which Mardette Perkins appeared
    - Another Part of the Forest, 1948 (Box 12)
    - Arsenic and Old Lace, undated (Box 12)
    - Captain Carvallo, 1952 (Box 12)
    - Dangerous Corner, 1949 (Box 12)
    - The Devil Passes, undated (Box 12)
    - Heartbreak House, 1950 (Box 12)
    - The Man Who Came to Dinner, 1949-1950 (Box 12)
    - My Sister Eileen, undated (Box 12)
    - Penny Wise, undated (Box 12)
    - Personal Appearance, undated (Box 12)
    - Ring Around the Moon, undated (Box 12)
    - See How They Run, undated (Box 12)
    - The Vagabond Players, 1950 August 20 (Box 12)
- Series IV. Personal Papers, 1948-1991; 1.46; (4 boxes)
  The series contains journals, photographs, printed material, clippings, and personal effects reflecting Perkins' personal life dating from 1948 to 1985. In her journals Perkins details her psychoanalysis with Dr. Altman. The journals are a window into Perkins' experience with anxiety and depression. Evidence of Perkins' affiliations with various universities and churches can be found in this series.
  - Journals, 1961-1971; 3 (Box 13)
  - Journals, 1973-1976, 1996; 7 (Box 14)
  - Deborah Perkins Cooper, Memorial Service program, 1979 July 24 (Box 15)
  - Helen Edmonds Perkins, Memorial Service program, 1980 July 26 (Box 15)
  - Charles Perkins, school schedule, papers, 1976-1977 (Box 15)
  - Certificate of Literacy from University of the State of New York, 1950 October 14 (Box 15)
  - Personal Reading Lists, circa 1985 (Box 15)
  - Postage Stamps, undated (Box 15)
  - Medication list, notebook, 1979 (Box 15)
  - The Neighborhood Playhouse School of the Theatre, catalogue, 1957-1958 (Box 15)
  - Wellesley College, printed material for 20th, 35th, 40th and 49th reunions, 1966-1991; 4 (Box 15)
  - St. Paul's Church, Richmond Virginia, notes, correspondence, newsletters, and sermons, 1976-1981; 3 (Box 16)
  - Rimbaud by Yves Bonnefoy, annotated by Mardette Perkins, 1973 (Box 16)
  - Clippings of Mardette Perkins, 1948-1950 (Box 16)
  - Clippings collected by Mardette Perkins on theatre, religion, and other topics, 1978-1985; 5 (Box 16)
  - Wedding portrait of Mardette Perkins, 1959 (Box 17 (Oversize))
  - Canadian Pacific Railroad Map, [1949] (Box 17 (Oversize))
  - Crucifix, wood, undated (Box 18 (Oversize))
- Series V. Audiovisual Material, 1961-1993; 0.67; (2 boxes)
  The series contains audio recordings, including Perkins reciting her poetry and commercials in which Perkins acted during the 1960s.
  Box 19 (audiocassettes): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Box 20 (film): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Mardette Perkins reciting her poetry (1 of 4), 1992-1993; 1; 00:44:19; There is high background noise on the tape. At about 44:20, the audio is mono. (Box 19, Item barcode 39002091394644)
    Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    This audiocassette includes a list of contents. The audio of the first three poems are prior to Mardette Perkin's stroke (3/9/1992). A note on the tape reads: note difference in voice. The list of contents are provided below.
    Side A / Side B
    1. "Sonnet of the Sun" retitled "Persephone", 1945-1991
    2. "Black Eruptions", 1990 March 31
    3. "Song of the Rose", 1981 March - October
    4. "Lost Generation" and "My Mother's Wedding Dress", 1992 October 21
    5. "Mysterium Trum[?]", 1992 October 21
    6. "Companions on the Journey", 1993 January 27
    7. "Calligraphy in the Willow", 1993 May 20-23
    8. "A Mother's Reflections and Variations on Her Son's Chinese [?], 1993 May 20
    9. "Bronze and Chocolate", 1984 January - 1985 February
    10. "Full Moon", 1971 July 10
    11. "Good Advice", 1974 January - 1985 March
    12. "Serafina", 1990 August 15
  - Mardette Perkins reciting her poetry (2 of 4), 1993 July; 1; 00:54:08 (Box 19, Item barcode 39002091394651)
    A list of contents are included below.
    13. "Shadow of the Albatross", 1985 November 3
    14. "Caress for the Blind Hour"
    15. "Mated", 1989 October 13
    16. "The Slave", 1985 February 13
    17. "Pittsburgh - 1942", 1973 May 24
    18. "Along the Housatonic: Journey Out of Madness", 1982 March 9
    19. "The Ghost of Hamlet's Dream", 1974 December
    20. "We Were Hungry and You Fed Us"
  - Commercials of Mardette Perkins, circa 1961; (1 16mm film) (Box 20)
    Contains television commercials in which Mardette Perkins appeared circa 1960's. Commercials include: All, Joy, Corn Flakes, Cashmere Liquid, White Cloud, Mrs. Barr, Vicks, Camay, Duncan Hines Cake Mix, Polaroid, apple sauce, and First Penn Bank.
    (film) Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Mardette Perkins reciting her poetry, "Companions on the Journey" (3 of 4), 1993 March 3; 1; 00:04:01 (Box 19, Item barcode 39002091394669)
  - Mardette Perkins reciting her poetry, Tape III (4 of 4), 1993 October 13 - 1994 February 2; 1; 00:57:19 (Box 19, Item barcode 39002091394677)
    The contents of the cassette are included below.
    27. "The Christmas Tree", 1982 January
    28. "Reunion", 1985 November
    29. "Siblings Arm in Arm", 1986 April
    30. "Death Said Thomas Mann in Venice", 1993 November
    31. "We Beseech Thee to Hear Us Good Lord", 1970 March